Register of the Paul W. Frillmann papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul W. Frillmann papers
1941-1971
75056
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 album box, 3 envelopes (3.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, orders, notes, and photographs relating to activities of the American Volunteer Group in China during World War II, American foreign relations with China, 1946-1950, and conditions in China during the Civil War. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Frillmann, Paul, 1911-1972.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1911 Born
1936-1941 Missionary, Hankow, China
1941-1946 Chaplain and liaison to General Claire Chennault, American Volunteer Group ("Flying Tigers"), and Office of Stratetic Services (OSS) operative
1947-1954 American Consul, Mukden, Peking, Shanghai, Hong Kong
1954 Senior Associate, Harold L. Oram Company
1972 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, orders, notes, and photographs relating to activities of the American Volunteer Group in China during World War II, American foreign relations with China, 1946-1950, and conditions in China during the Civil War.
China. Kong jun. American Volunteer Group.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; United States--Foreign relations--China.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1942-1971 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1946-1950
  - Unidentified, 1946-1967
  - Allman, N. F., 1949
  - Anderson, H. M., 1949
  - Baker, Gilbert, 1948
  - Ballachey, Frank, 1948
  - Barnes, George, 1946
  - Berkov, Robert H., 1947
  - Bourlin, D. G., 1944
  - Brewster, Harold N., 1948
  - Central Aircraft Manufacturing Co., 1942
  - Chao Shih-chai, 1946
  - Chase, A. S., 1946
  - Chen, Johnson, 1946
  - Chen, Shao, undated
  - Chennault, Claire L., 1948
  - Chi, T. D., 1946
  - China Foundation, The, 1948
  - Chou Tsi Ya, 1948
  - Clubb, O. Edmund, 1946
  - Columbia Country Club, Shanghai, 1948
  - Connors, W. Bradley, 1947-1948
  - Crow, W. H. (?), 1947
  - Davis, Mrs. Lewis, 1948
  - Drake, Waldo, 1949
  - Dzao, Mrs., 1948
  - Egan, William J. Convery, 1949
  - Fairbank, John K., 1946
  - Galkin, G., 1948
  - Gilpatric, Donald, 1948
  - Gow Mo-ch'uan, 1947
  - Gunn, Mrs. A., 1949
  - Handscomb, G. M., 1947
  - Havsky, S. B., 1948
  - Hopkins, Arthur H., 1949
  - Hsien Hsu-ming, 1947
  - Huang Chu-yong, 1948
  - Iverson, Lalla, 1948
  - Jones, Robert H., 1946
  - King, Basil and Lee Chun Fang, 1948
  - Klein, Otto, 1948-1949
  - Kuttner, F. A., 1949
  - Leber Chao Chia, undated
  - Leggate, Dr., 1947
  - Li Min Chin, 1947
  - Lie Chu, 1947
  - Liljestrand, S. H., 1966
  - Lin Chi-chun, 1948
  - Linthicum, Thomas, 1946
  - Liu, Hugo, 1946
  - Liu Sien-wei, 1949
  - Lurje, Walter, 1948
  - Mabie, Janet, 1949
  - Mahnke, Johanna K., 1948
  - Meng Chih, 1949
  - Muller, R. J., 1948
  - Musso, Victor, 1946
  - Newton, Elmer, 1949
  - North, Robert G., undated
  - Ou, Y. H., 1948
  - Patterson, L. D., 1947
  - Peoples, Jack, 1947
  - Rosholt, Malcolm D., 1965
  - Ryan, Dr., 1949
  - Scott, Richard C., 1947-1949
  - Service Recognition Board (Illinois), 1949
  - Sherrod, Bob, 1946
  - Shoemaker, Henry, 1947-1948
  - Sobbe, Hedwig, 1948
  - Stumpf, L., 1948
  - Tan Soo-hian, 1947
  - Tay, Paul, 1948
  - Time-Life, Inc., 1947
  - Tsui, T. L., 1946
  - United States. Department of State, 1946-1950
  - United States Education Foundation, 1948
  - United States. Veteran's Administration, 1946
  - Vietor, Dr. and Mrs., 1949
  - Walton, A., 1946
  - Ward, Angus, 1947
  - Williams, John M., 1971
  - Wilson, Earl J., 1949
  - Woodberry, Earle J., 1946
  - Yah Van (Kuen) Tsiang, 1948
  - Yan Chiang Ho, undated
  - Yang Tso-ngan, 1947
  - Yao, Mr., 1948
  - Yu Hsing, 1948
  - Yuan Lay, 1948
- CHINA. AIR FORCE. AMERICAN VOLUNTEER GROUP FILE, 1941-1969 (Box 2)
  Lists, correspondence with families of deceased members, and other material relating to the American Volunteer Group, arranged as listed.
  - General
    - Lists of deceased and burial sites
    - Lists of members
    - Lists of personal effects
  - Chaplain
  - Correspondence
    - 1941 September - 1942 July
    - 1942 August - 1943 May
  - Tiger Rag, The
- SUBJECT FILE, 1941-1950 (Boxes 2-3)
  Memoranda, reports, printed material, and other material, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Biographical material
    - Certificates, awards (Box 2)
    - Education records
    - Employment records
    - Forms
    - Miscellaneous
    - Notes, notebook
    - Printed material (Box 3)
    - Receipts, business records
    - Travel vouchers, passes, etc.
    - United States Army records
  - Birch, John
  - China - Communist Party
  - Miscellaneous
  - United States
    - Department of State
    - Department of the Army - Intelligence Section
    - Foreign relations - East (Far East)
    - Information Service (USIS)
      - General
        - Memoranda
        - Receipts
      - Korea
    - Office of Strategic Services (OSS)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1947-1951 (Box 4)
  - Three certificates, 1947, 1950-1951
- PHOTOGRAPHS, undated (Photo file)
  164 prints / 8 negatives / 3 envelopes / 1 oversize box
  - 7 prints of Paul W. Frillmann; 9 prints of Paul W. Frillmann and others; 30 prints of Paul W. Frillmann officiating at American Volunteer Group (Flying Tiger) funerals; 5 prints of American Volunteer Group burials; 2 prints of cemetery where American Volunteer group members are buried, undated (Envelope A)
  - 31 prints of unidentified scenes; 65 prints of unidentified people; 8 negatives, undated (Envelope B)
  - 10 prints of portraits of American Volunteer Group members; 2 prints of American Volunteer Group members; 2 prints of General Claire L. Chennault; 1 print of General Claire L. and Mrs. Anna Chennault with unidentified person, undated (Envelope C)
  - 1 photograph album, primarily prints of Chinese paintings; 1 picture of Paul W. Frillmann on woodblock, undated (Album fD)
- DECLASSIFIED U.S. GOVERNMENT RECORDS, 1945-1949 (Reading room workstation)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Available as PDF files. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by date of creation.
  - Records released in 2010, 1945-1949
    - Paul W. Frillman memo to Chief, SI, OSS, CT, "Report on Third War Area Activities,", 1945 May 12
    - Department of State transmittal to certain American diplomatic and consular offices regarding department's white paper on China, with letter from Dean Acheson to the president, 1949 July 29